Guide to the Sibley College reports, theses and course materials, circa 1889-1907.
Sibley College reports, theses and course materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Sibley College reports, theses and course materials, circa 1889-1907.
16-5-508
Sibley College of Mechanical Engineering and Mechanic Arts.
13 volumes.
Printed Materials, Research Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Course materials, theses, and other materials pertaining to Sibley College.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Three volumes of course materials: two volumes for the Course in Practical Mechanics, circa 1889-1896 (part 1: Wood working; part 2: Metal working), and one volume for courses in the Machine Design department (1903-1904). The Machine Design volume includes course outlines and sample problem sets with illustrations, some on blueprint paper.
Four volumes of student Master's theses for the Sibley College School of Marine Construction, labeled "Examples of work in design and special problems," 1900-1903. Included are theses by Charles H. Delany, Paul Percy Bird, Horace Warren Deved, J.D. Clair Smith, G. Kohler, Sidney Graves Koon, William Alphonso Rowe, Leonard Griffin Shepard, and Richard J. Donovan. The theses are copiously illustrated with tables and graphs, most on blueprint paper.
Also, six volumes (two copies, three volumes each) of student and faculty reports on mechanical equipment (dated 1902), illustrated with photographs, cyanotypes, graphs, and tables. Vols. 1-2 have spine title "Mechanical laboratory equipment, students' reports." Vol. 1 focuses on a description of the history, operation, buildings, and equipment of Sibley College's Dept. of Experimental Engineering. Vol. 2 consists of reports on tests of mechanical equipment. Vol. 3 has spine title "Investigation and research. Effect of cold rolling, Prof. H. Diederichs," and consists of a report on the effect of cold rolling on the physical properties of steel, prefaced by a letter from H. (Herman) Diederichs to R.H. (Robert Henry) Thurston, Director of Sibley College.
Also a Sibley Mechanical and Experimental Laboratory notebook from Raymond Curtis Warner Class of 1907 including textual notes, photographs, charts, and test results. Includes notes from courses taught by G. Carpenter, R. L. Shipman, W. Van Winkle, and H. W. Riley. Many of the tests were also conducted with fellow students Maurice Du Pont Lee and Huntly Harris Gilbert.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Sibley College of Mechanical Engineering and Mechanic Arts.; Bird, Paul Percy.; Delany, Charles H.; Deved, Horace Warren.; Diederichs, Herman, 1874-1937.; Donovan, Richard James, d. 1917.; Kohler, G.(George Melvin).; Koon, Sidney Graves.; Rowe, William Alphonso.; Shepard, Leonard Griffin, d. 1927.; Smith, J. D. Clair.; Thurston, Robert Henry, 1839-1903.; Sibley College of Mechanical Engineering and Mechanic Arts.School of Marine Construction.; Sibley College of Mechanical Engineering and Mechanic Arts.Dept. of Experimental Engineering.
Subjects:
Mechanical engineering--Study and teaching--New York (State)--Ithaca.; Marine engineering.; Steel.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Cyanotypes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Bound in brown morocco with gilt lettering.
CONTAINER LIST
- Course materials
  - Course in Practical Mechanics, pt. 1: Wood Working, ca. 1889-1892; Bd. Ms. 1+
  - Course in Practical Mechanics, pt. 2: Metal Working, ca. 1889-1896; Bd. Ms. 2+
  - Machine Design, 1903-1904; Bd. Ms. 3+
  - Raymond Curtis Warner laboratory notebook, ca. 1906-1909; Bd. Ms. 14+
    Also contains some later doodles relating to war and Hitler.
- School of Marine Construction: Examples of Work in Design and Special Problems (theses)
  Contains the texts and designs.
  - Charles H. Delany, "Balancing of Marine Engines", 1902; Bd. Ms. 4+
  - Paul Percy Bird, "Design of Machinery of About 4500 Horse-Power", 1900; Bd. Ms. 4+
  - Horace Warren Deved, "Design of a 10,000 I.H.P. Triple Expansion Marine Engine", 1903; Bd. Ms. 4+
  - J.D. Clair Smith, "Design of Marine Engine and Boilers of 1800 I.H.P.", 1903; Bd. Ms. 5+
  - G. Kohler, "Design of Marine Machinery of About 1000 Indicated Horse-Power", 1901; Bd. Ms. 5+
  - Sidney Graves Koon, "On the Longitudinal Strength of Steel Ships", 1903; Bd. Ms. 6+
  - William Alphonso Rowe, "The Design of a Ship", 1903; Bd. Ms. 6+
  - Leonard Griffin Shepard, "On the Design of a 1400 Ton Ocean Going Yacht", 1903; Bd. Ms. 7+
  - Richard J. Donovan, "Strength of Ships", 1901; Bd. Ms. 7+
- Reports
  - Department of Experimental Engineering Mechanical Laboratory Equipment, Students' Reports, v. 1, ca. 1902; Bd. Ms. 8++
    Presentation of the laboratory and its equipment (texts and photographs).
  - Department of Experimental Engineering Mechanical Laboratory Equipment, Students' Reports, v. 2, 1902; Bd. Ms. 9++
  - Investigation and Research. Effect of Cold Rolling, Prof. H. Diederichs, 1902; Bd. Ms. 10++
    Contains the report of tests (text, drafts, stats and photographs).
  - Department of Experimental Engineering, Mechanical Laboratory Equipment, Students' Reports, v. 1, copy, ca. 1902; Bd. Ms. 11++
    Copy 2. Presentation of the laboratory and its equipment (texts and photographs).
  - Department of Experimental Engineering Mechanical Laboratory Equipment, Students' Reports, v. 2, copy, 1902; Bd. Ms. 12++
    Copy 2.
  - Investigation and Research. Effect of Cold Rolling, Prof. H. Diederichs, copy, 1902; Bd. Ms. 13++
    Copy 2. Contains the report of tests (text, drafts, stats and photographs).